Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company records LSC.1434
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Minutes, 1924-1950, 1954-2009
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1925-1927 (Box 109, Folder 4)
    Executive Committee members William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr., J.H. Shackelford, A. Hartley Jones and Norman O. Houston met on August 3, 1925 to approve Nickerson's organization plan to give each Charter Member a Charter Member Certificate and to discuss bills and salaries. On November 27, 1925 the committee agreed on compensation for E.J. Johnson's work in the Oakland District. On June 29, 1926 the committee recommended that first employee Helen Beavers' salary be increased $10.00 per month beginning August 1st. Materials also include correspondence from Director of Agencies George A. Beavers, Jr. to the Executive Committee concerning a new business drive called President's Month and a report from Beavers concerning his trip to northern California to survey the following cities: Oakland, San Francisco, Fresno and Bakersfield.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1925-1931 (Box 109, Folder 5)
    The Board adopted By-Laws on February 28, 1925. Materials include Certificates of Contribution Membership application, Articles of Incorporation, a permit from the State Corporation Department to sell and issue Certificates of Contribution Membership. A special meeting was held on May 25, 1931 wherein the Board amended its Articles of Incorporation to reflect its name change from the Golden State Guarantee Fund Insurance Company to the Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1927-1931 (Box 109, Folder 6)
    Executive Committee minutes include correspondence from the Publicity Committee concerning ideas for a company emblem, a resolution in honor of the company's 6th anniversary, minutes from the Special Committee on Interest and Committee Salaries, monthly income statements and a letter to the Board from President Nickerson regarding his trip to Texas to meet with the Insurance Commissioner Tarver and Chief Deputy Carter to explore the possibility of Golden State's establishment there. Nickerson noted that Carter had lived for years in Abilene, "... one of the most Negro-hating centers in the State of Texas." Nickerson also noted that "On this trip I saw more black people than ever I saw in my entire lifetime. In the big cities, along the highways, in the small cities, they came out by the thousands."
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1928 May 8-1930 December 30 (Box 110, Folder 1)
    Materials include Executive Committee resolutions concerning the erection of a Home Office building, correspondence from President Nickerson on the recruitment and training of agents and Publicity Committee reports on outreach to the National Convention of the N.A.A.C.P. and the National Negro Insurance Association.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1930 March 3 (Box 110, Folder 2)
    Materials include minutes for the Annual Session at 4111 Central Avenue wherein a resolution passed which reduced the number of Board members from 15 to 9 members. The Board also amended the company's Articles of Incorporation and ballots for the election of Directors.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1931 January 9-1937 July 20 (Box 110, Folder 3)
    Materials include Vice President and Director of Agencies George A. Beavers, Jr.'s sales incentives such as the following themed production contests: Baseball, Track Meet, Big Game Hunt, Olympic Games and Football. Winners received awards such as trophies, cash, entertainment, premium hams and turkeys.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1931 March 2-1938 April 19 (Box 110, Folder 4)
    Materials include the Board's adoption of the resolution to change the company's name to the Golden State Mutual Life Insurance Company and the amendment of the Articles of Incorporation to clarify the company's purpose on May 25, 1931, an Executive Committee report concerning the creation of an International Department "... to consist of all Latin speaking people including Mexicans, Filipinos and South Americans in the State of California," and Norman O. Houston's narrative report of his trip to Oakland and Sacramento. The Minutes of the Eleventh Annual Regular Meeting on March 2, 1936 reflect the unanimous reelection of the following officers: President and Manager William Nickerson, Jr., Vice President and Director of Agency George A. Beavers, Jr., Vice President Simon P. Johnson, Secretary-Treasurer Norman O. Houston and Medical Director H.H. Towles.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1932-1938 (Box 111, Folder 1)
    Materials include notices of Annual Meetings, the announcement of the N.N.I.A. Convention contest where representatives who produce the highest amount of increase in combined debit will receive trips to Baltimore to attend the Convention, the loss of five cash boxes between the closing of the vault on May 23 and its opening on May 25, 1936 and correspondence from Secretary Norman O. Houston concerning the Board's approval of a resolution to change the number of Directors from nine to eight.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1937 November 2 (Box 111, Folder 2)
    Board members present at this meeting included H.H. Towles, S.P. Johnson, William Nickerson, Jr., George A. Beavers, Jr. and Norman O. Houston. Members discussed the proposed amendments to By-Laws, improved property locations, the Football Production Contest and the Home Office lighting problem. Typed and annotated By-Law amendments are attached to these handwritten minutes.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1938 April 26-1942 January 27; Records bound within a hardcover minutes book. (Box 111, Folder 3)
    Minutes include discussion of inviting the N.N.I.A. to Los Angeles as the company's guests during the 1939 session, the July 6, 1938 approval of a citation for Henry Armstrong, World's Featherweight and Welterweight Champion for his excellent representation of the citizens of Los Angeles, agreement that the Company participate in the Booker T. Washington Commemorative Stamp Program and Report on Conference with Insurance Commissioner Hon. A. Caminetti, Jr. on July 18, 1940.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1942 February 6-1945 June 25 (Box 111, Folder 4)
    Materials include notices of annual meetings, elections of Directors and Officers, the creation of Company Statistician positon and the abandonment of the Company Cashier position, Helen E. Hodge's title change from Cashier to Statistician, and discussion of facilities improvements such as the acceleration of the search for a new Home Office building.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1945 November 20-1947 February 18 (Box 112, Folder 1)
    The Board adopted a resolution in honor of the Company's deceased Founder-President William Nickerson, Jr. on November 20, 1945. During this meeting the Board amended numerous Company By-Laws such as "Article VII Officers" so that the officers of the Company shall be Chairman of the Board, President, one or more Vice Presidents, a Comptroller, Agency Director, Secretary, Treasurer and Medical Director. All resolutions at this meeting were adopted by unanimous consent including the elections of the following officers: Director of the Company Bertha B. Nickerson, Chairman of the Board George A. Beavers, Jr., President Norman O. Houston, Vice President H.H. Towles, Comptroller Norman O. Houston, Agency Director George A. Beavers, Jr., Secretary Edgar J. Johnson, Treasurer Bertha B. Nickerson, Assistant to Comptroller Helen E. Hodge, Superintendent of Agencies Arthur J. Williams and Assistant to Secretary Robert W. Smith.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1947 March 3-1950 January 24 (Box 112, Folder 2)
    The Executive Committee discussed the findings and determination in connection with architect Paul R. Williams' application concerning the Western Avenue and West Adams Boulevard property development on July 23, 1947. The Board of Directors approved Williams' fee for submission of building plans to the City of Los Angeles for the construction permit on February 24, 1948. The appraiser valued the total land area at $128,000. On May 12, 1948, President Norman O. Houston reported on his contact with artists who are qualified to paint the murals in the new Home Office lobby. The committee approved authorization to architect Paul R. Williams to create a contract on a fixed fee basis with artists Hale Woodruff and Charles Alston. The committee also approved a motion to negotiate a contract with sculptor Richmond Barthe to make a bronze bust as a permanent memorial for Founder-President William Nickerson, Jr.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1947 March 3-1950 January 24 (Box 112, Folder 3)
    The Committee approved the three year rental lease of office space at 4263 South Central Avenue to the Los Angeles Branch of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). On March 5, 1951 the Board approved personnel for membership on the following committees: Executive, Agency, Finance and Public Relations. On January 29, 1951 the Board reorganized its donations budget into the following sections: Life and Health Extension, General Welfare Contributions and Association Dues. The minutes record a list of organizations and donation amount by section.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1954 March 1-1958 January 1 (Box 113, Folder 1)
    At the Annual Membership Meeting on March 7, 1955, Secretary Edgar J. Johnson read a special report concerning President Norman O. Houston's March 1954 auto accident caused by an intoxicated driver on the highway in Texas. The accident occurred during a business trip while Houston was driving back to Los Angeles. It demolished his vehicle and caused critical injuries to him and the other occupants of his car. During this meeting, the Board also appointed personnel to the following committees: Executive-Finance, Agency, Public Relations, Cost Control and Budget, Claims Policy and Relationship and Salary. At the April 23, 1957 meeting, the Board discussed the recent labor dispute, the termination of California agents and GSM's agreement with the Insurance Workers of American AFL-CIO Union.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1958 March 3-1962 February 28 (Box 113, Folder 2)
    On October 27, 1959 the Board ratified the Agreement reached by the 1959 Negotiating Team with the IWIU, AFL-CIO. It was reported that the Agreement was ratified by the membership of the IWIU on October 21, 1959. At the January 26, 1960 meeting, it was reported that the Company received an award of excellence from the Life Advertisers Association for its "Historical Murals" booklet. The Board also discussed the lease or purchase of the IBM RAMAC (Random Access Method of Accounting and Control) and announced that Chairman Beavers had received the Carver Gold Award for his contributions to the field of Race Relations and Human Welfare. Ivan J. Houston was elected to the Board of Directors at the 35th Annual meeting on March 7, 1960.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1962 April 24-1966 March 7 (Box 113, Folder 3)
    At the January 22, 1963 meeting the Board approved Chairman Beavers' resolution that each Board Meeting shall include a statement concerning the offering of invocation or prayer based on its desire that this "... sacred practice be reflected in the recorded proceedings of our Board meetings and become a part of the written history of our Company." The Board paid tribute to President John F. Kennedy who was assassinated on November 22, 1963 and voted to close the Company office for business on November 25, the date of his funeral. Public Relations Manager William E. Pajaud attended the July 27, 1965 meeting to present drawings, layouts and plans for the GSM Art Collection in the Home Office lobby.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1966 July 26-1969 October 27 (Box 114, Folder 1)
    The Board passed a memorial resolution on July 26, 1966 to honor the life of A.J. "Kelly" Williams who began his career with the Company in 1933 at the Oakland District Office. The Executive Committee approved closing the Home Office and district offices on April 8 and 9, 1968 in memorial to Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. Chairman Norman O. Houston was joined by the entire Board at the July 15, 1969 meeting to express appreciation to Mrs. Helen E. Batiste for her 44 years of outstanding service as an employee. The Board endorsed the "Crisis and Commitment" statement dated October 13, 1966 and signed by Dorothy Height, Bayard Rustin, Whitney M. Young, Hobson R. Reynolds, A. Philip Randolph, Roy Wilkins and Amos T. Hall. GSM Co-Founder George A. Beavers, Jr. resigned as Chairman of the Board effective as of the October 25, 1966 Board meeting.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1969 December 15-1973 March 5 (Box 114, Folder 2)
    The Board elected Verna A. Hickman to fill the position of Treasurer on July 27, 1970 with the title Vice-President-Secretary and Treasurer. Also at this meeting, Ernest Shell pointed out the urgency of preparing a history of the Company from 1925 to publication while information resources are available in personnel of long tenure. The Board carried Shell's corporate history motion that this publication be considered a priority item in the 1971 budget. Chairman Houston recommended that Mrs. Bertha B. Nickerson be nominated as a Director Emeritus at the Annual Meeting on March 1, 1971 and that an inscribed plaque be presented to her. The Chairman noted that Verna A. Hickman was celebrating her 45th anniversary with Golden State Mutual at the July 19, 1971 meeting. The Board passed a resolution and commendation for her loyal and dedicated service to Golden State Mutual since she began as a clerk-typist on July 1, 1926.
  - Board of Directors file, 1970-1976 (Box 114, Folder 3)
    Corporate Secretary's file on the Board of Directors includes expense reports, meeting invitations, resolutions. correspondence, clippings and checklists. This file was maintained by two corporate secretaries: Verna A. Hickman and Amanda G. Lockett.
  - GSM Board Members list, 1925-1972 (Box 114, Folder 4)
    Board of Directors membership lists are organized chronologically by fiscal year.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1973 March 5-1976 October 25 (Box 115, Folder 1)
    At the close of the July 16, 1973 meeting President Houston reported that the 50th Anniversary activities will begin July 23, 1974 and run to July 23, 1975. The "Concept 50" program plans and the presentation of the trio concept were presented to the Board by Director of Public Relations William Pajaud. On October 22, 1973 the Board carried a motion to approve the following memberships for the Board of Directors of the Golden State Mutual Foundation: Ivan J. Houston, Ernest Shell, Larkin Teasley, Norman O. Houston, George A. Beavers, Jr., Edgar J. Johnson, Charles H. Matthews, Francis A. Kornegay, Verna A. Hickman, Byron Beverly, and Leonard M. Grimes, Jr. Chairman Norman O. Houston was absent from the March 1, 1976 meeting due to illness. Director Johnson brought to the Board's attention that this is the second time in the history of the Company that Chairman Houston has been absent from a Board meeting.
  - Resolution for the Formation of an Investment Committee, 1976 (Box 115, Folder 2)
    Materials include a copy of the resolution as originally adopted by the Executive Committee on December 9, 1970 and subsequently amended on August 4, 1976 and December 15, 1976.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1977 March 7-1980 October 27 (Box 115, Folder 3)
    The Board passed a resolution on March 7, 1977 that conferred upon Norman O. Houston the title of Honorary Chairman for life in honor of his service. It was reported at the July 25, 1977 Board meeting that the Company's Corporate History is "being brought to a close." On September 7, 1977 Vice President-Agency Director Stephen A. Johns reported to the Executive Committee that the Insurance Workers' International Union rejected the Company's final offer in negotiations and effective September 1, 1977, Golden State Mutual's California agents went on strike. The Executive Committee ratified and approved the action taken by Chairman Ivan J. Houston in his October 10, 1977 letter to Almena Lomax in which he enclosed a copy of the final GSM Corporate History manuscript and a check for $1,000, representing the balance due.
  - Annual Meeting file, 1968-1984 (Box 115, Folder 4)
    This Annual Meeting file was kept by the following Corporate Secretaries: Verna A. Hickman, Amanda G. Lockett and William E. Pajaud. Materials include correspondence concerning Annual Meeting attendance, committee member appointments, Annual Meeting logistics, Board of Directors nominations lists, Order of Business records, Confirmation of Attendance records, Annual Meeting Notices, Directors Resolutions on Amendment of Articles, Restated Articles of Incorporation and Certificate of Amendment of Articles of Incorporation.
  - Board of Directors file, 1978-1989 (Box 116, Folder 1)
    Materials include meeting notices, meeting agendas, Annual Meeting agendas, Action Program Control sheets, elected officers lists, nominations for Board of Directors, correspondence, copies of resolutions and Board Vice Chairman Ernest Shell's memorial program and obituary clipping from the Los Angeles Sentinel.
  - Annual Reports to the Board of Directors, 1979-1982 (Box 116, Folder 2)
    William Pajaud's copies of four Annual Reports to the Board of Directors from Chairman of the Board and Chief Executive Officer Ivan J. Houston. These reports include an introductory letter from Ivan J. Houston, highlight for the fiscal year, a list of administrative and policy-making activities, a list of retirements and deaths, and reports, summaries and analyses related to income, policies, investment activity, sources of income, operations and personnel strength.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1981 March 2-1985 March 4 (Box 116, Folder 3)
    The Executive Committee discussed the status of the Corporate History and the need for such a history on March 18, 1981. Chairman Ivan J. Houston announced at the June 3, 1981 Executive Meeting that he will go to Port Elizabeth, South Africa to speak to the National African Federated Chamber of Commerce. The Board adopted Edgar J. Johnson's memorial resolution in honor of Norman O. Houston's invaluable service and declared that this resolution "... be recorded in the official archives of this Corporation for the benefit of posterity." At the October 5, 1983 Executive Committee meeting, President Teasley reported that GSM had been approached regarding a possible merger with Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company of North Carolina. The committee carried a motion authorizing Mr. Teasley to further explore a possible merger and to obtain the latest copy of the insurance department examination report and a review of mortgage investments. On April 4, 1984, the Executive Committee discussed the sale of the Winston Mutual Home Office building in Winston-Salem and carried a motion to elect Winston Mutual Life President George E. Hill to the Golden State Mutual Life Board of Directors effective July 23, 1984.
  - Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company files, 1983 December 31-1984 August 23 (Box 116, Folder 4-8)
    Materials concern the Winston Mutual - Golden State Mutual merger and include GSM Executive Committee minutes, Winston Mutual Board of Directors and Executive Committee minutes, correspondence from GSM President Larkin Teasley and GSM Chairman and CEO Ivan J. Houston to Winston Mutual President George E. Hill, a Report on Examination of the Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company, a progress report from Teasley to Houston, agreements of employment, merger task transmittal sheets and Winston Mutual overview of agency operations.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 117, Folder 1)
    On July 23, 1984, the Board reported that there will be a luncheon to celebrate the Company's 59th Anniversary. Director Grimes suggested that a resolution be prepared and submitted to Congress on the Company's 59th Anniversary to be read into the congressional record. At the Executive Committee meeting on February 20, 1985, it was reported that the following officers of Golden State Mutual were re-elected to the Winston Mutual Life Insurance Company of North Carolina Board of Directors: Ivan J. Houston, Larkin Teasley, Charles L. James, Verdun Arnaud, Frank Summerfield, Elroy Bond and William E. Pajaud. The Board of Directors received 60th Anniversary mementos on July 22, 1985.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1985 March 4-1989 October 30 (Box 117, Folder 2)
    Chairman Houston reported at the March 20, 1985 Executive Committee meeting that plans are underway to celebrate the Company's 60th Anniversary on July 21, 1985 at the Home Office Auditorium in the form of a reception and a review of the Company's art collection. Mayor Tom Bradley will serve as the Honorary Chairman and Councilman Gilbert Lindsay, the General Chairman. On May 8, 1985, the Executive Committee unanimously carried a motion to adopt a resolution on the Reinsurance and Assumption Agreement by and between GSM and Winston Mutual Life. Director Helen E. Batiste was absent at the October 30, 1989 due to illness and in lieu of an invocation, a moment of silent prayer was observed in memory of Co-Founder and Director Emeritus George A. Beavers, Jr. who passed on October 12, 1989.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1986-1988 (Box 117, Folder 3)
    The Executive Committee carried a motion on August 13, 1986 to adopt a memorial resolution in honor of Mrs. Lola Beavers, wife of Co-Founder George A. Beavers, Jr. The Board of Directors held a special conference on October 26, 1986 at the Hyatt Hotel Wilshire where they discussed the Company's image, advertising, the status of black business and the loyalty of the black community. At the Board of Directors meeting on March 7, 1988, Chairman Houston presented a report in which he explained that 1987 was not a good year financially for the Company, its market had changed dramatically and that 1988 will be a critical year in the Company's history.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1986-1991 (Box 117, Folder 4)
    During the October 17, 1990 meeting, the Executive Committee resolved that Ivan J. Houston's retirement be effective December 31, 1990 and that Larkin Teasley be elected and appointed to the Office of President and Chief Executive Officer, effective January 1, 1991.
  - Executive Committee minutes, 1989-1993 (Box 117, Folder 5)
    At the October 17, 1990 Executive Committee meeting, President Teasley presented a resolution regarding Ivan J. Houston's retirement as GSM Chief Executive Officer. Houston was elected Chairman and C.E.O. on March 5, 1990, announced his intention to retire on December 31, 1990 and agreed to continue service as Chairman of the Board and the Executive Committee and as a Company consultant in order to perform actuarial duties as designated by the Board and the C.E.O. During the September 11, 1991 meeting, Senior Vice President George E. Hill announced that an inventory has begun on the Company's art collection. The Executive Committee carried President Teasley's motion to promote Isaac Snowden to the position of Director of Data Processing, effective January 1, 1993.
  - Investment Committee minutes, 1984-1993 (Box 118, Folder 1-5)
    Materials include minutes and Notices of Security Transactions.
  - Board of Directors minutes, 1990 March 5-1995 October 30 (Box 119, Folder 1)
    The Executive Committee met on January 11, 1990 and announced the passing of retired Assistant Vice President Mr. Mercer Z. Ray on January 6th, that Board member Helen E. Batiste is still in the hospital recuperating from brain surgery and that retired Vice President-Secretary Verna A. Hickman is also still recuperating.